<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Student Initiative | Jonathan Ratschat</title>
    <link>/tag/student-initiative/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/student-initiative/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Student Initiative</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Jonathan Ratschat 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon.png</url>
      <title>Student Initiative</title>
      <link>/tag/student-initiative/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Expert is Made, Not Born</title>
      <link>/post/an-expert-is-made-not-born/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/an-expert-is-made-not-born/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was failing. I had worked my ass off. But somehow, I did not see any success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was not that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t reaching anyone. I got meetings with interested potential clients. But after having had numerous pitches, I did not see any results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got rejected. Often. I heard all the excuses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sorry, we don&amp;rsquo;t have have any budget right now. Let&amp;rsquo;s talk in half a year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I talked with the relevant division. They don&amp;rsquo;t have time to organize something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your proposal sounds interesting. I&amp;rsquo;ll forward you to another part of the company where you&amp;rsquo;ll fit better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course, I never heard back from the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that time, I decided to work harder. To approach more clients. To get more meetings. Somewhere I had heard that hard work would ultimately pay off as a sales guy. Success was waiting for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But of course, nothing changed. The system that I had built was running, but not in my favor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day I met with one of the founders for lunch. All of a sudden, he said to me, &amp;ldquo;Jonathan, it&amp;rsquo;s not working, right?&amp;rdquo;. I responded, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m doing everything I can, but I don&amp;rsquo;t know what&amp;rsquo;s going on&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What he then told me was one of the best advice I&amp;rsquo;d ever been given.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Jonathan, I can&amp;rsquo;t help you. But I bet there is someone who can help you. Why don&amp;rsquo;t you ask Justin? He is one of the best sales guys I know&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was on fire. Justin, yeah, I knew this guy. Startup founder. Cool guy, approachable, and lots of experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overly motivated as I was, I not only reached out to him but also his sales head. One thing led to another, and I had two meetings scheduled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened? We talked a lot about my sales process. About every little detail that I had never thought of. After meeting both of them for 30 minutes each, I was able to point out the mistakes I had made. Not just the mistakes, but also the things I was not doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened then? I still put in the hard work. But this time, everything changed. Instead of zero offers, I had three on the table. Since we only had one spot open, I had to cancel two potential partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When looking back, these mistakes seem so obvious. But little did I know back then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had not asked anyone for advice when I started my new role. Everyone seemed to be determined that I was the very best candidate for this role. Therefore, it never crossed my mind to ask for help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, when I was not successful, I did not question my approach. I mean, I was approaching clients and meeting with them. It was just bad luck that I did not get the response that I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took someone else to open my eyes. And when my eyes were open, I was able to seek the advice I needed. And when I sought the direction I needed, my actions changed for good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;this-is-how-i-seek-advice&#34;&gt;This is how I seek advice.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just ask for it. When I have a problem that Google cannot solve, I think about who I can ask. Do I know anyone who could get me going in the right direction? If not, do I have a friend that knows a lot of people in this particular field?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I have identified someone that can genuinely help me, I sent a message. Straightforward. Where? Most often, they are acquaintances, so I either have their phone number, or I am connected on LinkedIn with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I state my problem. What is important here is that I am specific about my problem. That I cannot solve it by myself. Also, I show respect by asking this particular person for advice. I trust this person to be able to help me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I ask for is a phone call. Most often, they are glad to help. I mean, who doesn&amp;rsquo;t like to help someone who is actively seeking one&amp;rsquo;s advice? Someone who shows respect and trust?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know it takes courage to ask an acquaintance or even a stranger for help. But ultimately, their input can help me to solve problems that I could not have solved by myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I&amp;rsquo;ve learned through this experience is that hard work is not always the solution. That I&amp;rsquo;m not an expert just because my job description says so. Therefore, I am allowed to get advice. And this advice can help me to get to the very next level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions or comments, feel free to reach me via the contact field or 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://linkedin.com/in/jonathan-ratschat&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working for Free Improved My Life in 3 Great Ways</title>
      <link>/post/working-for-free-improved-my-life-in-3-great-ways/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/working-for-free-improved-my-life-in-3-great-ways/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was first published on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/working-free-improved-my-life-3-great-ways-jonathan-ratschat/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money is essential as a student, and time is limited, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if I told you that joining a student initiative has been one of the best decisions that I have made in the last year? Please hear me out. I know that your schedule is more than full. But maybe, only maybe, it’s a decision that is also right for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I want to share is my journey with a so-called student initiative. Not any student initiative. A student initiative driven by a specific purpose and great people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time I heard about TechAcademy was through a friend. At that time, my life was hectic, so I asked some questions and probably quickly switched the topic. “Good for him that he has the time to start a new student initiative without getting paid for it” I thought to myself. But since I was too focused on my own life, I did not hear him out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some months passed, my life changed dramatically, and of a sudden, I saw an announcement on LinkedIn that this initiative was finally ready to take off. This time, I was more than interested. Why? Because I recognized it had a clear purpose. And this purpose related to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what does TechAcademy do? TechAcademy prepares students for the digital future. Each semester, they offer 70 students from all faculties the opportunity to acquire programming skills in the fields of Data Science and Web Development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had learned some lines of code during my first semester, but I’ve never had the opportunity to apply it. Without having any projects or people that were using this programming language, I quickly stopped. But remembering that I once wanted to improve my skills, I could directly see that they were offering a valuable program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what did I do? I quickly reached out to one of the founders and offered my help. Why? I don’t know. Maybe I wanted to meet some new people, and perhaps I wanted to be part of something bigger than me. As I said, I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward one and a half years. What has happened in this time is fantastic. I got to meet so many inspiring people, learned a lot professionally, and we, as a team, have been able to have an impact on the lives of over 190 students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;here-are-the-three-things-that-i-got-from-joining-a-student-initiative&#34;&gt;Here are the three things that I got from joining a student initiative.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-community&#34;&gt;1. Community&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When working at my student initiative, I got to meet a lot of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, there is my team with whom I organize everything. I won’t lie. Being in a student initiative involves a lot of work. But through that work and the shared purpose, I got close to my team. We see each other every week, which led to new friendships. And these people are cool, driven, and inspiring — precisely the people I want to call friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I met so many participants. Each and everyone is different. At TechAcademy, we are open to every faculty. Why? Because each and everyone lives in a digital world that is exponentially changing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, we do not have just business students that participate in our program. I mean, when and where do I meet mathematics, physics, teaching, or humanities students all in one place? I find it interesting to get to know different perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gratefully remember one Ph.D. student in archaeology that joined our program. She wanted to learn Python to write an algorithm to classify ancient vases. How crazy is that?!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-professional-experience&#34;&gt;2. Professional experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have learned so much in my “job” at TechAcademy. It feels like working in a small startup. I need to fulfill specific responsibilities. If I don’t do it, I let my team down. There’s nobody else to blame. Therefore, I learned to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I have the freedom to bring in my ideas. I can make a difference. We are 15 people right now. Therefore, my voice gets heard. And on my team, there are only three of us. We can do our job as we please. Nobody tells us how we should do things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can try out new methods to approach potential partners. We can try out new negotiation techniques. In the end, we can assess what works and use it from that point on. Compare that to work in a big corporation as an intern. There you don’t question the status quo. There you just do what your colleagues ask you to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, I have learned much more at TechAcademy than in any internship. As I said, you have to make stuff happen. My responsibility is to create partnerships with companies. Through these partnerships, we can offer our participants valuable insights on how digitalization is lived in practice. Also, we can finance our initiative through these partnerships since our program is entirely free of charge for students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why have I learned much more than in any other internship? I approach companies, have initial phone calls and meetings with them. I negotiate contracts, and I have to maintain the relationship once the contract is signed. Most importantly, I need to make sure that we, as a student initiative, solve a problem for the company. If not, they won’t work with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I compare this with two sales-related internships that I had. There I prepared (potential) customer information and conducted market research. If I got fortunate, I was allowed to join a call or a meeting as a “fly on the wall”. I mean, I am thankful for the experience and that I was paid, but these are indeed two different worlds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-caring-for-others-by-giving-back&#34;&gt;3. Caring for others by giving back&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t remember which book it was (probably one of Tony Robbin’s books), but there, the author made clear that happiness can be achieved through helping others. That there is nothing more fulfilling than going the extra mile for another human being. To step back from one’s ego and to care about someone who’s not yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have found truth in these words. Of course, being in a student initiative has had a significant impact on my own life. But when you think about it, I am sacrificing my time so that students can participate in the best-possible program that we can create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The students are enabled to learn a new programming language. For many of them, it’s the first time that they have used a program other than Word or Excel. They don’t know what machine learning or data science is. But when they participate in our program, a whole new world has opened to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, they meet so many people who become good friends. Not everyone is good at meeting new people, but we make sure that they have the opportunity to get out of their comfort zone. One friend told me last semester:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It is so hard for me to meet new people. Now, after having been here every other week, I have met people with whom I go to the canteen or have study groups.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can assure you that this has had a significant impact on her life. I bet that many other stories are similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe someone finds a new passion. Another one creates a living out of that passion. Maybe one person can finally write his or her empirical bachelor or master thesis without getting nightmares. Another one finds friends for life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, by itself, is very motivating. I am part of something that creates value in the lives of many people. It’s not about me, it’s about them. And this is something that I love about my work at TechAcademy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, joining TechAcademy had a meaningful impact on my life. I am thankful for everyone that made this journey possible, for all the people that I have met, and all the memorable days that I have spent with this initiative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey goes on, and maybe, just maybe, I have inspired you to look for opportunities at your university or your neighborhood. Of course, TechAcademy is not the only cool initiative there is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions or comments, feel free to reach me via the contact field or 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://linkedin.com/in/jonathan-ratschat&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TechAcademy</title>
      <link>/project/techacademy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/techacademy/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
