<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sales | </title>
    <link>/tag/sales/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/sales/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Sales</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon.png</url>
      <title>Sales</title>
      <link>/tag/sales/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Expert is Made, Not Born</title>
      <link>/post/an-expert-is-made-not-born/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/an-expert-is-made-not-born/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was failing. I had worked my ass off. But somehow, I did not see any success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was not that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t reaching anyone. I got meetings with interested potential clients. But after having had numerous pitches, I did not see any results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got rejected. Often. I heard all the excuses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sorry, we don&amp;rsquo;t have have any budget right now. Let&amp;rsquo;s talk in half a year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I talked with the relevant division. They don&amp;rsquo;t have time to organize something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your proposal sounds interesting. I&amp;rsquo;ll forward you to another part of the company where you&amp;rsquo;ll fit better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course, I never heard back from the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that time, I decided to work harder. To approach more clients. To get more meetings. Somewhere I had heard that hard work would ultimately pay off as a sales guy. Success was waiting for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But of course, nothing changed. The system that I had built was running, but not in my favor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day I met with one of the founders for lunch. All of a sudden, he said to me, &amp;ldquo;Jonathan, it&amp;rsquo;s not working, right?&amp;rdquo;. I responded, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m doing everything I can, but I don&amp;rsquo;t know what&amp;rsquo;s going on&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What he then told me was one of the best advice I&amp;rsquo;d ever been given.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Jonathan, I can&amp;rsquo;t help you. But I bet there is someone who can help you. Why don&amp;rsquo;t you ask Justin? He is one of the best sales guys I know&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was on fire. Justin, yeah, I knew this guy. Startup founder. Cool guy, approachable, and lots of experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overly motivated as I was, I not only reached out to him but also his sales head. One thing led to another, and I had two meetings scheduled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened? We talked a lot about my sales process. About every little detail that I had never thought of. After meeting both of them for 30 minutes each, I was able to point out the mistakes I had made. Not just the mistakes, but also the things I was not doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened then? I still put in the hard work. But this time, everything changed. Instead of zero offers, I had three on the table. Since we only had one spot open, I had to cancel two potential partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When looking back, these mistakes seem so obvious. But little did I know back then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had not asked anyone for advice when I started my new role. Everyone seemed to be determined that I was the very best candidate for this role. Therefore, it never crossed my mind to ask for help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, when I was not successful, I did not question my approach. I mean, I was approaching clients and meeting with them. It was just bad luck that I did not get the response that I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took someone else to open my eyes. And when my eyes were open, I was able to seek the advice I needed. And when I sought the direction I needed, my actions changed for good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;this-is-how-i-seek-advice&#34;&gt;This is how I seek advice.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just ask for it. When I have a problem that Google cannot solve, I think about who I can ask. Do I know anyone who could get me going in the right direction? If not, do I have a friend that knows a lot of people in this particular field?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I have identified someone that can genuinely help me, I sent a message. Straightforward. Where? Most often, they are acquaintances, so I either have their phone number, or I am connected on LinkedIn with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I state my problem. What is important here is that I am specific about my problem. That I cannot solve it by myself. Also, I show respect by asking this particular person for advice. I trust this person to be able to help me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I ask for is a phone call. Most often, they are glad to help. I mean, who doesn&amp;rsquo;t like to help someone who is actively seeking one&amp;rsquo;s advice? Someone who shows respect and trust?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know it takes courage to ask an acquaintance or even a stranger for help. But ultimately, their input can help me to solve problems that I could not have solved by myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I&amp;rsquo;ve learned through this experience is that hard work is not always the solution. That I&amp;rsquo;m not an expert just because my job description says so. Therefore, I am allowed to get advice. And this advice can help me to get to the very next level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions or comments, feel free to reach me via the contact field or 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://linkedin.com/in/jonathan-ratschat&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
